A Guide to the Edson Egbert Healy papers, 1863-1932
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Edson Egbert Healy papers, 1863-1932
Library of Virginia
54040
.225 cubic feet (1 box) Photocopies.
Edson Egbert Healy
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Allison Stabile, Brentwood, Tennessee.
Biographical Information
Edson Egbert Healy was born 3 November 1844 in Newburgh, Ohio, to John Healy (1805-1880) and Daty Hand Hubbard Healy (1810-1881). Educated in public schools, Healy enlisted as a clerk in the United States Commissary Department during the Civil War. Healy and his brother John Sullivan Healy (1842-1908) were captured during a Confederate raid on New Creek, West Virginia, on 28 November 1864. The brothers were held in Castle Thunder in Richmond, Virginia, until their release in an exchange on 5 February 1865. Edson Healy returned to Newburgh where he operated a store with his father and his brother. He married first Esther Ellen Taylor (1845-1911) on 18 February 1869, and they had four children, three of whom lived into adulthood. He married second Ida Rockingham Weinman (1857-1938), 3 February 1916. Healy died 1 April 1932 in Cleveland and was buried in Woodland Cemetery.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1863-1932, of Edson Egbert Healy (1844-1932) of Newburgh and Cleveland, Ohio, containing correspondence, memorandum books, photographs, telegrams, and other papers documenting the capture of Healy and his brother John Sullivan Healy (1842-1908) while working as clerks for the United States Commissary Department during a Confederate raid on New Creek, West Virginia. Obituaries, photographs, and other documents detail Edson Healy's life in Cleveland after the Civil War. Collection includes transcripts.
Contents List
- Inventory (Folder 0)
- Photographs of Edson Egbert Healy (Folder 1)
- Photograph of John Sullivan Healy (Folder 2)
- Photograph of Edson Egbert Healy in Healy Brothers Store (Folder 3)
- Letter from John Healy, Newburgh, Ohio, to Edson Egbert Healy and John Sullivan Healy, Camp Piatt, Kanawha County, West Virginia, 13 July 1863 (Folder 4)
- Letter, Captain Seymour Brownell, Camp Piatt, to Edson Egbert Healy, 5 August 1863 (Folder 5)
- Letterhead created by Edson Egbert Healy for Captain Seymour Brownell, U.S. Commissary Department (Folder 6)
- Obituary for Seymour Brownell, Detroit Free Press[?], April 1908 (Folder 7)
- Letter, Elam Moe, Macomb County, Michigan, to Edson Egbert Healy, New Creek, Hampshire County, West Virginia, 29 February 1864 (Folder 8)
- Letter, John Sullivan Healy, Clarksburg, West Virginia, to Edson Egbert Healy, New Creek, 9 April 1864 (Folder 9)
- Letter, Edson Egbert Healy, Camp Piatt, to John and Daty Healy, Newburgh, 29 June 1864 (Folder 10)
- Letter, Edson Egbert Healy, Cumberland, Maryland, to John and Daty Healy, Newburgh, 13 July 1864 (Folder 11)
- Letter, Edson Egbert Healy, Harper's Ferry, West Virginia, to John and Daty Healy, Newburgh, 21 July 1864 (Folder 12)
- Telegram, Captain O. B. Kerlin, Cumberland, to John Healy, Cleveland, 3 December 1864 (Folder 13)
- Letter, Captain M. M. Laughlin, Parkersburg, West Virginia, to Edwin M. Stanton, Secretary of War, 7 January 1865 (Folder 14)
- Clipping, National Tribune, regarding Confederate raid on New Creek, undated (Folder 15)
- Clipping, Richmond Daily Dispatch, regarding civilians captured during General Rosser's raid and their imprisonment at Castle Thunder, 8 December 1864 (Folder 16)
- Letter, Captain O. B. Kerlin, Cumberland, to Edwin M. Stanton, Secretary of War, 12 December 1864 (Folder 17)
- Letter, William S. Purgit, New Creek, West Virginia, to John Healy, Newburgh, 19 December 1864 (Folder 18)
- William S. Purgit diary (transcript), 1865 (Folder 19)
- John Sullivan Healy, Castle Thunder, Richmond, Virginia, to Julia R. Wheeler, near Cleveland, 6 January 1865 (Folder 20)
- Captain O. B. Kerlin, Cumberland, to Jennie [Julia] Wheeler, Newburgh, 10 January 1865 (Folder 21)
- Certificate for Healy brothers upon release from Castle Thunder, Lieutenant Colonel John E. Mulford, Fort Monroe, 6 February 1865 (Folder 22)
- Andrew Jackson Spencer, Fairfax Station, Virginia, to Edson Egbert Healy, 15 July 1865 (Folder 23)
- Andrew Jackson Spencer, Fairfax Station, to Edson Egbert Healy, 27 July 1865 (Folder 24)
- Andrew Jackson Spencer, Newburgh, to Edson Egbert Healy, Clarksburg, 18 August 1865 (Folder 25)
- Andrew Jackson Spencer obituary, Cleveland Plain Dealer, 28 February 1899 (Folder 26)
- Obituary program for Edson Egbert Healy, Miles Avenue Christian Church, Cleveland, 7 April 1932 (Folder 27)
- Photograph of Healy Brothers Store, Newburgh, ca. 1900 (Folder 28)
- Article on Newburgh, Cleveland Plain Dealer, 30 March 1931 (Folder 29)
- Edson Egbert Healy obituary, Cleveland Plain Dealer, 3 April 1932 (Folder 30)
- John Healy papers at Western Reserve Historical Society (Folder 31)
- Edson Egbert Healy memorandum book, 1859-1866 (Folder 32)
- Art by Edson Egbert Healy for his wife Esther Ellen Taylor Healy for their wedding, 18 February 1869 (Folder 33)
- John Sullivan Healy Civil War service record (copies from National Archives), 1890-1908 (Folder 34)